本期《造物小百科》
On how it's made.
铝箔
Aluminium foil.
如何轻松地把三吨重的铝锭变成眼前这片箔?
How do we get from a three-ton ingot to this in one easy motion?
滑雪板
Snowboards.
这种混合设计, 其精密程度得益于古老工艺与计算机技术
A hybrid design that owes its precision to age-old techniques and computerised technology.
隐形眼镜
Contact lenses.
尖端科技遇上金刚石车床, 整个过程快得出奇
Cutting-edge science meets diamond-headed lathes in a surprisingly quick process.
还有面包
And bread.
从法棍到圆顶白面包再到贝果,
From baguettes to bloomers to bagels,
现代面包工厂犹如一场精心编排的交响乐
the choreographed symphony which is a modern-day bread factory.
铝箔成为厨房必备品已有我们无法追忆的年头
But first, aluminium foil has been a kitchen standard for longer than we can remember.
它是理想的烹饪工具, 因为导热性能极佳
It's a perfect cooking tool because it's an ideal heat conductor.
从烤箱里的烤肉到冰箱冷冻, 用途数不胜数
From the roast in the oven to the freezer, it has a myriad of uses.
但一块巨大的固态铝是如何
But how does a huge block of solid aluminium get
变成薄如纸的箔片?
transformed into a paper-thin sheet of foil?
制造铝箔需要反复
The manufacture of aluminium foil requires the repeated
碾压大块铝锭
thinning out of a large block of aluminium.
这块巨型铝锭的旅程始于天然气熔炉的高温熔炼
This massive ingot's journey begins by being blasted in a natural gas furnace.
熔化这块二十七吨
It takes three to eight hours to melt this twenty-seven
重的铝块需要三到八小时
thousand kilo lump of aluminium.
回炉熔炉的温度高达骇人的
The remelting furnace operates at a staggering seven
七百五十摄氏度
hundred and fifty degrees centigrade.
不能有半点差错, 因为铝的熔点高达六百
No chances are taken, because the fusion temperature of aluminium is six hundred.
六十摄氏度
And sixty degrees centigrade.
取一部分铝液浇入这个小模具, 制成样品
A portion of aluminium is poured into this small mould to make a sample.
几秒内便凝固, 样品可用于检测以验证
Solidifying in just seconds, the sample allows for testing to verify the contents of
所配合金的成分
the prepared alloy.
接下来的工序让液态铝
The next encounter takes the now liquid aluminium
经流槽流入出铝井
through a trough to the tapping well.
杂质在专用容器中被过滤掉
Any impurities are filtered out in special receptacles.
浇入铸锭模后, 喷水加速冷却过程
Poured into ingot moulds, water accelerates the cooling process.
铝液随即淬火, 铝锭随之凝固
The molten aluminium is quenched and the ingot solidifies.
现在重型机械上场了
Now the heavy machinery gets to work.
每块铝锭都极为庞大, 长达四点四米
Each ingot is massive, measuring four point four metres in length.
重达惊人的七千五百公斤,
It weighs a whopping seven thousand five hundred kilos,
必须用行车吊起, 精准地放到
so it has to be handled by overhead cranes and placed on
专用托板上
special plates with absolute precision.
去壳机削去铝锭表层三毫米的厚度
The crust removing machines skimmed three millimetres of the ingot's thickness.
这样可消除杂质, 得到完美的镜面效果
In doing this, impurities are eliminated to achieve a perfect mirror finish.
冷却去壳刀具的液体痕迹必须全部清除
All traces of the liquid used to cool the decrusting knives has to be removed.
去壳刀具：铣削铝锭表层的刀具
下一道工序压力最大
The next process is the most stressful.
铝锭的碾压工序开始了
The thinning of the ingot begins.
铝块被热轧辊碾碎
The aluminium block is crushed by the hot mill rollers.
连轧辊本身的温度都在
Even the rollers operate at temperatures between four
四百五十五到五百四十摄氏度之间
hundred and fifty five and five hundred forty degrees centigrade.
首先要核实施加在铝锭上的压力
Firstly, the pressure on the ingot must be verified.
压力过大会使铝锭开裂, 那就得重头再来
If too great, it could split this block, and they'd have to start again.
温度太高, 铝锭有粘在轧辊上的风险
The heat is so intense that the ingot risks sticking to the mill's roller.
为此要使用一种润滑剂
A lubricant is used to prevent this.
它含百分之九十五的水和百分之五的油
That's ninety five percent water and five percent oil.
从四十五厘米的厚度起步,
Starting from a thickness of forty five centimeters,
每经过一次轧制, 铝锭就变得更薄
the ingot becomes increasingly thinner with each pass through.
铝板可能需要在
The aluminium slab may have to pass through the
在碾轧辊之间来回十六次, 才能达到所需厚度
crushing rollers sixteen times before the right thickness can be achieved.
此时铝锭厚度已达七厘米,
The ingot now measures seven centimeters in thickness,
但还必须压到仅剩半厘米
but still it has to get down to just half a centimeter.
现在铝锭厚五厘米, 长度超过九米
Now the ingot is five centimeters thick and measures over nine meters in length.
铝板经传送带送往最后的碾轧工序
The plate takes its last journey over a conveyor to the final milling stages.
厚度足以进行卷绕时,
Sufficiently thin to proceed with spooling,
铝板自身卷绕成完美的圆柱形
the plates wrap themselves around to make perfect cylinders.
随后被送往冷轧机,
They're then sent to the cold rolling mill,
在那里进一步压薄
where they're reduced even further.
现在到了最精细的环节
Now comes the most delicate stage.
铝片已经薄到可能
The aluminium sheets have become so thin they risk
因冷轧所需的张力而破裂
being broken by the tension needed.
因此将铝片对折, 避免断裂
For the cold rolling, so the sheet is doubled to avoid this breakage.
最后再调整一次轧机设定, 就能得到
One last alteration in the mill settings will create a
厚度恰好符合厨房级铝箔要求的铝片
sheet with exactly the thickness required for kitchen grade aluminium foil.
为完成整个流程, 箔片两侧
To finalise the process, the edges of the foil sheet,
因受损而皱褶的边缘,
which have become damaged and crinkled,
要用刀具切掉一厘米宽的窄条
are removed with a knife that slices a one centimetre thin strip.
铝卷被裁成所需的宽度,
The roll is cut to the desired width,
一块巨型铝锭最终产出的铝箔长达
and one huge ingot has produced foil measuring twelve
十二点七公里
point seven kilometres in length.
接下来, 看看行家的装备
Next up, the tools of the trade.
对滑雪板玩家而言,
For snowboarders,
就像所有优雅的运动, 看似轻松实则不易
like all graceful sports, nothing is as easy as it looks.
制造这些流线型的装备同样如此
The same can be said for manufacturing these sleek pieces of kit.
高手或许知道顶级滑雪板如何制成, 那其他人呢?
The pros may know how the best boards are produced, but what about everyone else?
这里有一份滑雪板制作的内部指南
Here's an insider's guide to making snowboards.
滑雪板是冬季运动爱好者的挚爱
The snowboard is the delight of winter sports enthusiasts.
核心结构就是一块简单的薄木板
At its core, it's a simple thin sheet of wood.
根据所制板的类型, 可选用多种木材
Various types can be used depending on the style of the board being made.
固定器必须牢牢装在板上,
Bindings have to be firmly attached to the board,
所以要钻孔装入预埋件, 固定器将固定其上
so holes are drilled for inserts to which the bindings will be secured.
模板可确保钻孔精准
A template allows for precise drilling.
厚板可能过硬, 所以宽度至关重要
A thick board can be too rigid, so width is all important.
刨削使板材达到所需厚度
Planing reduces the board to the required depth.
随后一道成型工序精修板的轮廓
A shaping procedure then refines the board's contours.
此刻板材仍完全平整, 没有任何弧度
At this point, the board is still perfectly flat with no curvature at all.
板材须竖直存放, 等待下一道工序
The boards have to be stored upright to await their next step.
现在要固定嵌入木中的铝制预埋件
Now, aluminium inserts must be secured, which are embedded in the wood.
这层薄薄的玻璃纤维能更好地支撑预埋件
This thin sheet of fiberglass affords better support for the inserts.
尚未成型的板材被夹在工作台上,
The still embryonic board is clamped to a bench,
以便进行精细加工
enabling precision work to be carried out.
涂上环氧树脂这种粘性极强的胶水
Epoxy, an extremely strong adhesive, is applied.
在室温下涂覆到玻璃纤维上
to the fiberglass at room temperature.
随后必须除去多余的环氧树脂, 并消除所有气泡
It's then essential to remove any excess epoxy and to eliminate all air bubbles.
板面由坚韧的塑料制成,
The top part of the board is made of a resistant plastic,
采用巧妙的丝网印刷工艺涂覆
applied by an ingenious silk screen process.
随后, 一把小刮板把底色油墨均匀刮涂在板上
Then, a small squeegee spreads a coat of the base colour ink evenly across the board.
每次涂刷称为一遍
Each application is called a pass.
颜色必须一种一种地加
Colours have to be added one at a time.
现在板材需要固化
Now, the board must be cured.
将施以极大压力
Extreme pressures will be used.
模具闭合时, 板材被压出所需的弧度
When the mould is closed, the board is given the desired curve.
模具产生的热量使板上的环氧树脂固化变硬
Heat generated from the mould makes the epoxy on the board set and harden.
现在板材已成所需形状, 从模具中取出,
Now the right shape, the board is removed from the mould,
多余的环氧树脂和木料用带锯切掉
and any excess epoxy and wood are removed by a bandsaw.
为切出漂亮利落的边缘,
To achieve a beautifully clean cut,
锯条每切五十块板就更换一次
the saw blade is changed after every fifty boards.
这是高精度的活, 由人工完成
It's highly precise work and carried out manually.
随后丝网印刷机再次登场,
Then the silk screen press is brought into action again,
这次涂上另一种颜色——红色
as it applies another colour, this time the red.
现在要给滑雪板加上保护层
Now the snowboard must be protected.
一层极薄的清漆喷淋将形成坚固的保护膜
An ultra thin shower of varnish will form a hardened shield.
板材从这道幕帘下穿过,
The board passes beneath this curtain,
随后进入烘干机, 待上六小时
and then moves into a dryer for a six hour stay.
砂磨去除板缘多余的清漆
Sanding removes surplus varnish from the edges of the board.
在板上重新钻孔, 以对准
New holes are pierced into the board to locate the
生产初期安装的预埋件
inserts installed at the beginning of production.
这台砂光机去除固化
This sander removes imperfections in the hardened
清漆上的瑕疵, 为第二次涂漆做准备
varnish and prepares the board for its second varnish coating.
随后砂磨塑料板底, 得到理想的光洁度
Then the plastic base is sanded to obtain the desired finish.
板材经过检查, 用刀片验证各涂层
The board is checked, and a razor blade verifies that the different coats are
之间粘合良好
well adhered to one another.
为增添奢华质感, 部分板材还嵌有蚀刻铝饰片
For a luxury touch, selected boards get an engraved aluminium insert.
至此, 滑雪板终于可以上场了
The board is now finally ready for action.
这家工厂每天生产超过五百块
With over 500 snowboards in 30 different models
三十种不同型号的滑雪板, 为玩家提供
produced each day, this factory offers the snowboarder the tools to
施展技艺的工具
express their skills.
《造物小百科》接下来播出:
Coming up on How It's Made:
隐形眼镜, 从太空时代的新奇之物到二十年间
contact lenses from space age and exotic to everyday
人人可用的日常用品
acceptance in just 20 years
还有从法棍到圆顶白面包的面包,
and bread from baguettes to bloomers,
现代面包工厂犹如一场精心编排的交响乐
the choreographed symphony of a modern day bread factory.
广告之后再见
See you after the break.
欢迎回到《造物小百科》
Welcome back to How It's Made.
稍后我们看看平凡的面包在上架超市之前
Later we look at what goes into the humble loaf before
经历了什么, 但首先,
it reaches the supermarket shelves, but first,
二十年前它们还被视作太空时代的新奇之物, 如今已是日常用品
20 years ago they were seen as space age and exotic, now they are an everyday item.
胆小者仍难以想象将
The squeamish among us still couldn't imagine having
一样东西如此贴近我们的眼睛,
something so closely located to our eyes,
但隐形眼镜彻底改变了人们看待
but contact lenses have revolutionised the way people
自己的方式, 名副其实
see themselves, quite literally.
隐形眼镜已问世一百多年
Contact lenses have been in existence for over a century.
起初完全坚硬, 如今已变得如明胶般柔软
At first completely rigid, they have become as flexible as gelatine.
这些小圆片用于制作各种颜色的软性聚合物隐形眼镜
These small discs are used to make soft polymer contact lenses in a variety of colours.
当然, 一切从患者的验光单开始,
Of course, the place to start is with a patient's prescription,
数字化之后, 整个流程得以启动
which has been digitised for the process to begin.
第一步是先对镜片成型进行数据处理控制
The first stage begins with the data processing control of the shaping.
车床开始加工镜片的内曲面,
The lathe commences by shaping the inner curvature of
转速达每分钟六千转
the lens, rotating at 6,000 revolutions per minute.
它配备了一颗工业金刚石
It's armed with an industrial diamond.
它加工内表面, 即接触角膜的部分
It shapes the inner surface, the part that touches the cornea.
圆片不能有任何瑕疵, 随后
The disc must be free from any imperfection and is
用极细的研磨膏抛光
polished with a super fine abrasive paste.
抛光至关重要, 因为它能保证
Polishing is an essential step because it guarantees
佩戴舒适, 视力清晰
excellent comfort and perfect vision.
技术员用极其精密的量具测量镜片厚度
A technician measures lens thickness with an extremely precise gauge.
接着加工外表面,
The outer surface is then shaped,
即接触眼睑的部分
the part which touches the eyelid.
镜片用一种特殊蜡粘在旋转臂上,
The lens is glued to a spinning arm with a special wax,
之后用超声波装置去除
which will be removed later by an ultrasound device.
蜡在几秒内塑造成型
The wax is moulded in just seconds.
现在加工镜片的外径, 由
The outer diameter of the lens is now shaped as the
计算机控制的机械臂轻松切掉多余的聚合物并抛光
computer-controlled arm effortlessly cuts away the excess polymer and is polished.
这种高速进行的抛光
This polishing, done at high speed, calls for an abrasive paste,
需要研磨膏、一些油和一个小棉球
some oil, and a small polyester cotton-like ball.
这台设备一次抛光多片镜片,
This apparatus polishes several lenses at a time,
整个过程仅需六十秒
a step that takes only 60 seconds.
随后技术员打磨镜片边缘
A technician then polishes the rims of the lenses.
聚合物随后水化, 使其变得柔软
The polymer is then hydrated to make it flexible.
镜片需浸泡在酸碱度平衡的
Lenses remain immersed in a balanced.
生理盐水中二十四小时
pH saline solution for 24 hours.
镜片吸饱液体后膨胀,
The lens becomes engorged with liquid and expands,
达到所需尺寸
reaching the desired proportions.
接下来检查镜片
Next, the lenses checked.
用光学地形图仪验证
An optical topographer is used to verify whether the
镜片光焦度的分布是否足够精确
spread of the optical power in the lens is precise enough.
每一步, 这些柔软易碎的镜片都必须加倍小心地拿放
At every step, the soft, fragile lenses must be handled with the greatest of care.
这台称作焦度计的装置
This unit, called a fronto focal meter,
焦度计：测量镜片屈光度的仪器
是一种计量设备, 用于验证镜片的光学精度
is a metering device which verifies the optical precision of the lens.
镜片至此制作完成, 经清洗后
Lenses are now completed and are cleaned,
放入装有盐溶液的容器中储存
then stored in containers filled with salt solution.
药瓶用硅胶盖和铝盖严密封口
The vials are perfectly sealed with a silicon cap and another of aluminium.
随后放入灭菌器, 在
Then they are placed in a sterilizer at a temperature
一百二十一摄氏度的温度下加热一个半小时
of 121 degrees centigrade for an hour and a half.
令人惊叹的是, 若不开封, 内容物可保持无菌
Amazingly, the contents will remain sterile for a period of up to
长达七年
seven years if not opened.
虽然制作一片镜片需经过十四道工序,
Although the production of a lens involves 14 steps,
但若不计水化过程,
if you exclude the hydration process,
十五分钟就能做出一片
it only takes 15 minutes to make one.
从这些简单的彩色圆片,
From these simple colored discs,
一件精心打造的高精度科技产品就能瞬间改变一个人的生活
a crafted precision piece of technology can transform a person's life instantly.
法棍、恰巴塔、皮塔饼、切片白面包、圆顶白面包,
Baguette, ciabatta, pita, white slice, bloomer,
贝果、全麦黑麦、黑麦粗面包
bagel, wholemeal rye, pumpernickel.
种类无穷无尽, 面包的名声亦如此
The list is endless, as is the bread's reputation.
就连古埃及人和古希腊人都是烘焙大师,
Even the Egyptians and Greeks were master bakers,
但他们会对现代面包工厂
but how would they react to the choreographed symphony
这场精心编排的交响乐作何感想?
that is the modern day bread factory?
在工厂规模上制作面包, 绝非一件可以掉以轻心的差事
The art of bread making on a factory scale is a job not to be taken lightly.
需要希斯·罗宾逊式的奇思妙想, 才能让所有
It takes Heath Robinson-like imagination to make all
希斯·罗宾逊：英国漫画家，常画复杂机械
传送带、滑轮和刀具协同运作
the conveyors, pulleys and knives to work in tandem.
整个流程从六千公斤面粉开始
The journey starts with six thousand kilos of flour
从防护格栅倒入
being poured through a protective grill.
在加入原料前, 面粉先储存在三十六个巨型容器中
Thirty-six enormous containers store the flour before the ingredients are added.
这些揉面槽花三小时发酵酵母,
For three hours, these kneading troughs ferment the yeast,
面团最终将在此发酵膨胀
where the dough will eventually rise.
利用时机与蛮力的结合,
Using a combination of timing and brute force,
这台巨型搅拌机揉面八分钟
this huge mixer kneads the dough for eight minutes.
重达惊人的一千公斤,
Weighing a whopping one thousand kilos,
面团被倒入一个大桶
the contents are emptied into a large tub.
面团被倾倒到一个滑送系统上
The dough is emptied onto a slide system.
机器底部的小孔让面团流出
A small hole at the bottom of the machine allows the dough to escape.
随后, 两只机械臂把面团切成面包大小的面团块
Then, two mechanically operated arms cut the dough into loaf-sized pieces.
传送带接着把面团送往下一站
One of many conveyor systems then transports the dough onto its next destination.
在这里, 面团块被搓成圆球, 更便于加工
Here, dough pieces are rolled into balls, which can be more easily worked.
面团球随后撒上面粉, 防止它们在
The dough balls are then floured to prevent them from
运输和成型过程中相互粘连
sticking during their transportation and when they're molded.
运输途中面团得以静置, 让酵母发挥作用
During transport, the dough can rest, allowing the yeast to act.
面团随后被折叠并卷起
The dough is then folded and rolled.
这台机器每秒可处理三个,
The machine can handle three per second,
每小时总量达一万一千五百个
for a total of eleven thousand five hundred an hour.
面团被擀成恰好一条面包的大小, 落入烤模
The dough is rolled out to the exact loaf size and falls into baking molds.
这台机器用来制作热狗面包
Different-sized holes on this machine mean hot dog rolls.
这些小面团球须先纵向整形并发酵, 才能入模
These little dough balls have to be shaped lengthwise and fermented before molding.
热狗面包以完美的对称被机械塑形
In perfect symmetry, the hot dog rolls are mechanically shaped.
面团块之间不能相互接触,
Dough pieces must not touch one another,
所以由一只小机械臂将它们隔开
so they're spaced apart by a small mechanical arm.
回到面包房, 下一道工序开始了
Back at the loaf bakery, the next step is starting.
面团块卧在烤模底部,
Squatted down at the bottom of the molds,
进入醒发箱,
the dough pieces go into the proofer,
在四十二摄氏度
where they rise for an hour at forty-two degrees
百分之七十湿度的环境中发酵一小时
centigrade and at seventy percent humidity.
随后在二百五十五摄氏度
Then they bake for twenty.
的温度下烘烤二十分钟
minutes at two hundred and fifty five degrees.
烤好后, 面包呈金黄颜色
When finally baked, the loaves are a golden colour.
随后传送带再次接管
Then the conveyors take over again.
真空系统把面包从模具中吸出
A vacuum system draws the loaves from their molds.
接着放到另一条传送带上冷却
Then they're placed on another conveyor to cool.
引导系统负责把面包送往面包房各处
A guidance system takes care of carrying the breads to various sections of the bakery.
冷却充分后, 面包进入切片机
When well cooled, breads go to the slicer.
它每分钟能切六十五条面包
Which cuts sixty five loaves a minute.
它们由两厘米宽、四十
They are sliced by two centimetre wide and forty
厘米长的钢锯条切片
centimetre long steel saw blades.
机器随后把面包快速送往最后
The machines then speed the loaves onto their last
工序——包装, 在这里以每分钟六十五条的速率自动包装
stage, packaging, where they are automatically packed at sixty five per minute.
现在可以装运出厂了
They're now ready for shipping.